<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>🗂 Cardiovascular System on Anesthetips NCE Board Prep</title>
    <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/index.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in 🗂 Cardiovascular System on Anesthetips NCE Board Prep</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Ischemic Heart Disease</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/ischemic_heart_disease/ischemic/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/ischemic_heart_disease/ischemic/index.html</guid>
      <description>Ischemic Heart Disease Ischemic heart disease happens when there is an imbalance between myocardial oxygen supply and demand.
Factors contributing to a decreased oxygen supply:
Oxygen demand For patients with ischemic heart disease undergoing non-cardiac surgery, the Lee Revised Cardiac Index should be used to determine overall risk and help determine if further optimization is necessary.
Lee Revised Cardiac Risk Index 1 High Risk Surgery defined as intraperitoneal, intrathoracic, or suprainguinal vascular.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Valvular Heart Disease</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/valvular_heart_disease/valvular/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/valvular_heart_disease/valvular/index.html</guid>
      <description>Valvular Heart Disease Reference the 2020 ACC/AHA Guideline for the Management of Patients With Valvular Heart Disease: A Report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Joint Committee on Clinical Practice Guidelines Cross-section of heart pumping Let&amp;rsquo;s start by looking at the normal anatomy and the function of each part. The heart is divided into 4 chambers (2 Atrium / 2 Ventricles) with a septum dividing the right and left heart.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Congenital heart defects</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/congenital_heart_defects/congenital/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/congenital_heart_defects/congenital/index.html</guid>
      <description>Congenital heart defects There are many different congenital heart defects that can present in a child. Most of these conditions must be corrected in early life to allow for growth and development. It is helpful to group them by their defining characteristics.
Right &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Left Left &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Right Mixing Lesions Obstructive Lesions Tetralogy of Fallot VSD Tricuspid Artresia Coarctation of the Aorta Pulmonary artresia ASD Anomalous venous return Aortic/mitral stenosis Eismenger complex PDA Transposition of great vessels Interrupted aortic arch READING: Cote 1 p.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Cardiac conduction and rhythm abnormalities</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/conduction/conduction/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/conduction/conduction/index.html</guid>
      <description>Cardiac Cycle The cardiac cycle runs from the beginning of one hearbeat to the beginning of the next. The cycle begins in ventricular diastole just after the end of the t-wave on the ekg. The ventricles are passively filling with blood from the atria. The next phase (atrial systole) begins with atrial contraction which should show a p-wave on the ekg waveform. Ventricular systole quickly follows afterwards with a QRS complex now showing on the ekg waveform.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Cardiovascular and peripheral vascular complications</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/cardiovascular_complications/complications/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/cardiovascular_complications/complications/index.html</guid>
      <description>Cardiovascular and peripheral vascular complications Cardiac System The cardiac system consists of the heart and the blood vessels and is responsible for delivering nutrients to the body and removing waste products.
DanielChangMD revised original work of DestinyQx; Redrawn as SVG by xavax Hypertension Classification 1 Classification SBP DBP Normal &amp;lt;120 &amp;lt; 80 Prehypertension 120–129 &amp;lt; 80 Stage 1 130–139 80–89 Stage 2 ≥ 140 ≥ 90 Heart Disease DanielChangMD revised original work of DestinyQx; Redrawn as SVG by xavax 2</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Cardiovascular Infectious diseases</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/infectious_disease/infectious/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/infectious_disease/infectious/index.html</guid>
      <description>Infective Endocarditis (IE) Risk factors include:
Intravenous drug use Heart valve disease Congenital heart disease Heart valve surgery Previous history of IE Dental procedures For dental procedures involving the gingiva, area around the teeth (periapical), or needing incision of the oral mucosa, antibiotic prophylaxis is warranted if:
The patient has prosthetic cardiac valves or prosthetic material was used for valve repair (rings, chords, or clips) The patient has a previous history of IE The patient has an unrepaired cyanotic congenital heart defect The patient has had a cardiac transplant Rheumatic heart disease The most commonly acquired heart disease in people under the age of 25.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Pericardial diseases</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/pericardial_disease/pericardial/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/pericardial_disease/pericardial/index.html</guid>
      <description>Pericarditis Typically at least two of the following criteria should be present for a diagnosis of pericarditis:
Characteristic chest pain Sudden onset, retrosternal, and exacerbated by inspiration. Often lessened by leaning forward or sitting in upright position. Pericardial friction rub A high-pitched scratchy or squeaky sound heard best at the left sternal boarder. Suggestive EKG changes Wide-spread upward concave ST-segment elevation and PR-segment depression. Pericardial effusion TEE is recommended to rule out effusion and cardiac tamponade Treatment Treatment for acute pericarditis secondary to a non-viral identifiable cause is treatment of the underlying cause.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>❤️‍🩹 Cardiomyopathy and heart failure</title>
      <link>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/cardiomyopathy/cardiomyopathy/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nceboardprep.com/basic_sciences/anatomy_physiology_pathophysiology/cardiovascular/cardiomyopathy/cardiomyopathy/index.html</guid>
      <description>Cardiomyopathy and heart failure AI generated image of elderly man with heart failure Cardiomyopathy is a disease of the heart muscle that affects the ability of the heart to pump blood effectively. It can be classified into several types, including:
Dilated cardiomyopathy: The heart becomes enlarged and weakened, which leads to a decrease in its ability to pump blood. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: The walls of the heart muscle become thickened, which can make it harder for the heart to pump blood.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>